<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Product Design, Responsive Web Design, UX Design, Belfast Northern Ireland | Jordan Moore</title>
    <description>Product designer, responsive web designer and UX designer in Belfast, Northern Ireland, specialising in user experience and accessible design
</description>
    <link>http://jordanm.co.uk/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://jordanm.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jul 2018 09:30:14 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Jul 2018 09:30:14 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Meditation Mind Log After a Long Break</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I returned to meditation practice this morning for the first time in a long time. I felt that I’d be more experienced, know to expect a rough start and not to chase foolish goals. The mind chatter was much louder and more ridiculous than I anticipated. Here is a log of probably what is a small percentage of thoughts that appeared during the session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used Kevin Rose’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oakmeditation.com&quot;&gt;Oak Meditation app&lt;/a&gt; for the first time. I’ve had it on my iPhone homescreen for a quite a while as a visual reminder to return to the practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about past failures with meditation and my shallow breathing making it difficult to pick a point to focus on&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about whether the narrator was human or synthesised voice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Concluded he’s human&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about whether he is getting paid for this or whether he’s doing it out of the kindness of his heart&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Concluded he’s probably kind&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about a focus point of the breath again. My nose seems to work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about how taking deeper breaths would work, but would be forced and the forcing of those breaths would cause light-headedness and would be a distraction in themselves&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about failing because of busy thoughts, corrected this thought with Dan Harris’ “bicep curl for the brain” quote.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about trying not to think about those things and return to the breath&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about how I can’t seem to keep a clear mind for one iteration of in-pause-out&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about how I would know if I did&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Congratulated myself for getting to 3 iterations undistracted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Told myself off for congratulating myself as that was a distraction from the breath&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about yesterday’s meetings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about today’s to do list&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decided that can wait&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Congratulated myself for deciding they could wait&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decided to stop congratulating myself and return to the breath&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about silence for 3-4 iterations of the breath&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Was thinking about silence a thought in itself?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focused intensely on the breath&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about the words “This is all there is” that manifested from nowhere&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about where it came from.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought it was cool and that I should probably Tweet about that&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No. Return to the breath&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Congratulated myself for not pursuing enlightenment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decided to stop congratulating myself and return to the breath&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Would enlightenment be like a natural DMT trip? Or at least what my impression of what that looks like?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about how that might be true and how that might have shaped ancient cultures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about the breath&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about the instructor’s words to “Relax and let the mind wander”… or did he mean “wonder?”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about observing myself from the outside&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about where the mind sits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about how this session has been a disaster&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about how long was left&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about how it’s all a learning experience and how I couldn’t even switch those thoughts off&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about “This is all there is” again and quickly decided this was a low point rather than some sort of miniature enlightenment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about returning to the breath&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about what might happen if I return to the breath successfully and actually manage to hold it and then the session ends&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about how I wanted the session to be a few minutes longer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought about the room, my surroundings, my to-do list&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of session.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jul 2018 01:00:01 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://jordanm.co.uk/2018/07/20/meditation-notes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jordanm.co.uk/2018/07/20/meditation-notes.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Industry Fatigue</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/shylands/status/1019302186554200064&quot;&gt;Tweet from Steven Hylands&lt;/a&gt; caught my attention and got me thinking about my outlook on the digital design landscape, or more specifically my approach to learning new things in this space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have spent the last year or so avoiding any sources of design news aggregators including dedicated sites, Twitter accounts and various Medium publications. It wasn’t an overly conscious decision, it just sort of happened that I fell out of the loop, realised later that I fell out of the loop and then decided it wasn’t a loop I was interested in getting back into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My honest opinion is that I don’t feel like I’d miss any monumental leaps in our industry if I stopped checking design news or missed out on some new framework or build tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are of course things worth your time and deep consideration, and there are distractions. Profound new thinking and movements within our industry - the kind that fundamentally shifts the way we work in a positive new direction &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; worth your time and attention. Other things are distractions. I put new industry gossip, frameworks, software and tools firmly in the distractions category. This is the sort of content that exists in the padding between big movements. It’s the kind of stuff that doesn’t break new ground and it doesn’t make or break your ability to do your job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an over-simplified timeline of the industry movements that I have witnessed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web standards&lt;/strong&gt; (1998)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web 2.0&lt;/strong&gt; (~2002)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Responsive design&lt;/strong&gt; (2010)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design Systems&lt;/strong&gt; (~2015)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Next Big Thing™&lt;/strong&gt; (20××) &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the big fundamental leaps in how we make and how we have made things and lots of time in between them. If you have been in the industry during any of these movements, it was hard to miss any one of them. My reassuring message is that &lt;strong&gt;the important stuff finds you&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New tools&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, software, frameworks and hot takes on design matters dominate feed aggregators and I secretly think a lot of authors consciously utilise FOMO - not in the sense that you’re missing out on something important, but the idea that you’ll fall behind in how to do your job. This is simply not true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-side-note-on-future-design-jobs&quot;&gt;A side note on future design jobs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is if you dedicate yourself to keeping up with these tools, or worse, dedicating yourself to &lt;strong&gt;specialising&lt;/strong&gt; in them, you will be replaced by the next thing. In fact, when design becomes so formulaic that it paves the way for automation and then for artificially intelligent design unless you bring something innately human to the table, you too will be replaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing about that concerns me though. You could spend your time trying to fight the machines (the systems, the automation, the artificial intelligence) but the reality is that it works faster than you, it works harder than you and it’s going to be cheaper than you. It’s a pointless fight. Choose instead a different battlefield - one that isn’t about low-value, replaceable design and that is about high-value problem solving for deep human needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;structured-serendipity&quot;&gt;Structured serendipity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to feel bad for not keeping up with design matters. My interests drifted towards big, broad topics that I have spent my life avoiding such as psychology, philosophy and economics. I am consuming a lot of material across each of these topics and many others in my personal time, not for any other reason other than a quest for knowledge. I’m nowhere near an expert or a beginner for that matter in any of the aforementioned topics, but what I did start to notice over time was that I was finding concepts from these completely separate fields started manifesting in my design work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jasonzweigwsj&quot;&gt;Jason Zweig&lt;/a&gt;, a journalist for the Wall Street Journal wrote about varying what you learn and varying where you learn it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;New associations often leap out of the air at me this way. More intriguing, others seem to form covertly and lie in wait for the opportune moment when they can click into place. I do not try to force these associations out into the open; they are like the shrinking mimosa plants that crumple if you touch them but bloom if you leave them alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serendipity is a human concept that can’t/won’t be easily replicable by machines. Exploring new ground outside of our industry is fuel for serendipity, and thankfully my interests beyond acquiring new design knowledge are proving very useful in that regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My industry fatigue didn’t reveal itself through my work (I actually enjoy what I do a lot). It came about because I felt that there wasn’t anything new to learn within the field. Purposefully branching out into other fields has got me excited about designing with new perspectives on things and different approaches from beyond our bubble. I can’t say that I miss industry news… I actually feel like a better designer because of the choice to consciously sidestep it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just give me a nudge when the next big movement happens, okay?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;My guess is Automated Design &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I reckon there is a Moore’s Law of design tools. The number of design tools probably doubles every two years. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jul 2018 01:00:01 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://jordanm.co.uk/2018/07/20/industry-fatigue.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jordanm.co.uk/2018/07/20/industry-fatigue.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mapping User Experiences to Individuals Using the Big 5 OCEAN Personality Traits</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Big Five Personality Traits, sometimes referred to as the five factor model (FFM), is a model commonly used by psychologists to describe individual personalities. The original model was constructed by Ernest Tupes and Raymond Christal in 1961&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but it didn’t reach mainstream academic audiences until the 1980s and early 90s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multiple sets of independent researchers on human personality arrived at the same conclusion in naming the five factors that generally predict and explain behaviour which indicates the factors are valid as far as we know today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of the five factors (O,C,E,A,N) are scored between 1-100 according to the individual ranked against average scores after completing a series of questions (&lt;a href=&quot;https://openpsychometrics.org/tests/IPIP-BFFM/&quot;&gt;try it out for yourself&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The five factors are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;small-caps color-red&quot;&gt;Openness&lt;/span&gt; - this trait describes someone’s appreciation for art, adventure, inventiveness, creativity, sensitivity to beauty, likely to hold unconventional beliefs - things of an abstract nature. I personally sit on the 95th percentile for openness which seems abnormally high, but most people in the design industry tend to rank quite highly in this factor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;small-caps color-red&quot;&gt;Conscientiousness&lt;/span&gt; - a sense of self-discipline, desire for achievement, tendency to defy measures impeding the route to success, orderly, attention to detail&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;small-caps color-red&quot;&gt;Extraversion&lt;/span&gt; - mostly describes what kind of social animal you are, the ability to start conversations, talking to a variety of people at a party, ability to assert themselves, extraverts rather than introverts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;small-caps color-red&quot;&gt;Agreeableness&lt;/span&gt; - sensitivity towards others, empathy for the emotions of others, interested in people and the desire to make people feel at ease, giving up time for others, kind, generous, trusting, optimistic about the intentions of others&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;small-caps color-red&quot;&gt;Neuroticism&lt;/span&gt; - negative emotions such as anger, anxiety, depression, easily stressed and irritated, worrying, prone to mood swings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every person maps differently to each of the OCEAN personality traits, and having an understanding of how others around you correlate is beneficial to your interactions with them. Not everybody is comfortable being open about the specific scores on each of the factors, particularly as some indicate socially negative traits such as anxiety and depression. Before co-founding our product design studio, each of the directors took the Big Five Personality test as a means to a) see how aligned/unaligned we were in our own individual personalities and b) as a means of empathising with each other in recognising our strengths and supporting our weaknesses. I understand that not everybody would be comfortable sharing something that is so personal to the individual, but we found this exercise has eradicated any talk of &lt;em&gt;“I don’t understand [person]’s point of view”&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;“I don’t get where [person] coming from”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-persona-conundrum&quot;&gt;The Persona Conundrum&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the tools and methodologies within the field of user experience are flawed in that they do not address concerns beneath a user group level. A truly meaningful experience would speak to the &lt;strong&gt;individual&lt;/strong&gt; rather than taking a one-size-fits-all blanket approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are great at understanding the needs and desires of groups of people, but even personas - the UX tool designed to help empathise with specific users - always bring us back into solutions that scale up to cater for groups based on the assumed needs of a single user. Designing an experience for Sarah, a junior shop assistant who likes long walks, often leads that the majority of users become Sarah and her intended experience is their experience. Job Stories are a relatively new entry into this space where they fix the problem of personas splitting audiences, getting in the way of shared goals. Job Stories are a good means of orienting towards tasks and for that reason remain compatible with an OCEAN approach to UX where Job Stories address universal functional requirements. It leaves room for a presentational layer and certain functional elements catered for individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;practical-applications&quot;&gt;Practical Applications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applications could adapt their interfaces to individuals. Let’s imagine a fitness app with a audio guided run feature. Users in the upper percentiles of conscientiousness may benefit from the orderly, disciplined commands of a drill sergeant and from an app that stretches their goals slightly beyond their comfort zone pushing the user to compete at their best. For people on the other end of the conscientiousness scale, a softer approach would be necessary along with positive reinforcement to help them be the best that they can be without pushing them into territory that alienates them or makes them feel inadequate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same could apply for language and labels used within interfaces. Perhaps some colours appeal to certain personalities? Maybe there are images that intimidate people that inspire other sets of people?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the differences between individuals along OCEAN factors studies have shown that individuals high in agreeableness (people who give up time for others, make people feel at ease) are less likely to negotiate salary increases within their company. Perhaps we can create applications that help people move towards desired outcomes in adjusting elements in their personality that may be impeding on particular life goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;potential-dangers-and-opportunities&quot;&gt;Potential dangers and opportunities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest challenges in pursuing this untapped area of UX is gathering the data required to determine a person’s scores along the Big Five Personality Traits. It’s not exactly ideal to have users answer a full personality test under the promise of a better user experience on the other side of this unique onboarding experience, and it’s certainly not ideal to gather this data in any way that negatively affects a user’s privacy. Maybe it’s something that happens over time where certain actions can produce a score against the OCEAN factors, or games, puzzles and quizzes may unlock this type of information. There is work to be done and design problems to figure out here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there’s the question of how you store this information and what exactly you do with it. I don’t believe it is necessary to store this data on servers or let any company see a user’s scores. That is for the individual to know and for the product experience to react to it. It is potentially dangerous territory, but then again, so is everything we do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If ethics is about the question of how to act, and designers help to shape how technologies mediate action, designing should be considered ‘ethics by other means.’
Every technological artefact that is used will mediate human actions, and every act of design, therefore, helps to constitute moral practices.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;small-caps&quot;&gt;P. P. Verbeek, What Things Do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, every design decision you make is loaded with your intent and bias. We’re already knee deep in the danger game whether you have realised this sobering fact already or not. Another one of the major challenges is engineering objectivity into this process, and whether this field is explored further or not, we should look to engineer objectivity into our work regardless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-next&quot;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m at the mystery stage of the knowledge funnel as described by Roger Martin in his 2009 book The Design of Business&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I have identified that this is an area with great potential and the next steps are to build heuristics to see if we can mine the mystery for insights with the eventual hope of turning the research into a reliable, replicable algorithm give us the capability to create and resonate with the people who use the things we make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Five_personality_traits&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Five_personality_traits&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;P. P. Verbeek, What Things Do, 2009 (Page 69) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;R. Martin, The Design of Business, 2009 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jun 2018 10:12:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://jordanm.co.uk/2018/06/06/intro-ocean-ux.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jordanm.co.uk/2018/06/06/intro-ocean-ux.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Managing Daily Tasks</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing my to-do list for the day is a key part of my morning routine and essential to state setting and priming. Before I have a chance to get distracted by emails and other notifications vying for my attention I sit down with my morning coffee and write down the tasks I want to complete for the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use elements from &lt;a href=&quot;http://bulletjournal.com&quot;&gt;Ryder Carroll’s Bullet Journal&lt;/a&gt; to list out today’s tasks. Each task starts with a bullet point followed by a short description of the task. When completed the bullet point is crossed out so it changes from “•” to “×”. If I didn’t finish a task and I still consider it to be a valuable thing to do I move it to tomorrow’s list by replacing the bullet point with “&amp;gt;” indicating that the task has been deferred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the task is delegated or can be deleted from the list before starting, then it gets a nice, satisfying line through it. Using this system means that when reviewing my list at the end of the day I get a quick visual reference ensuring every bulleted task has been in some way and nothing slips through the net.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can go deeper with Bullet Journalling using tools like the Ryder’s Future Log for planning goals for the month, but I found that in practice navigating between pages became more frustrating than helpful. I found the most value in the daily task management part of the system so I have no qualms about utilising only that part of the Bullet Journal methodology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-why-not-software&quot;&gt;So why not software?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of biggest advantages is where it falls short for me in managing daily tasks. Software is faster than pen and paper. It’s easy to create a new task and add it to your list, which makes it easy to fill your list with things to do without a chance to properly think through the value of each task. I have been through countless task manager and to-do list tools to find one that sticks but in the end, I have always come back to pen and paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike a physical book, has to compete for your attention amongst other open apps, windows and browser tabs. I remember using a popular app based on the Getting Things Done (GTD) methodology and thinking it was working for me as I logged numerous tasks rapidly and proceeded to get to work. However, the problem started as soon as I started working on the tasks I had just set myself. The app would be hidden under multiple windows and sometimes I would go for days before realising it was still open with old, irrelevant tasks (and some forgotten items).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such apps allow you to set due dates and notifications, but I find they take me out of my current flow and I end up working the app rather than the app working for me. You don’t want to end up in a situation where you have to bend to fit the opinions of an app - what happens if you decide to change your to-do writing style or system? The software probably wants you to do it a certain way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-pen-and-paper&quot;&gt;Why pen and paper?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The great thing about pen and paper is its inefficiency&lt;/strong&gt;. It takes time to write the list, and that’s the beauty of it! Editing is clunky and it gets annoying when you have to rewrite tasks that you need to move from day to day. For that reason, it encourages taking time to write better, more realistic goals. is too forgiving in that regard, pen and paper hold you more accountable and it promotes thinking through big tasks and breaking them down into achievable subtasks that can be done today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a good old fashioned notebook has the additional advantage of taking your eyes off the screen. That pause enforces a small step back and seeing the bigger picture. It’s therapeutic.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 23 Mar 2018 09:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://jordanm.co.uk/2018/03/23/managing-daily-tasks.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jordanm.co.uk/2018/03/23/managing-daily-tasks.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Released&amp;#58; Wipe Screen</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jordanm.co.uk/img/wipe-screen.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wipe Screen screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jordanm.co.uk/wipescreen&quot;&gt;Wipe Screen&lt;/a&gt; attempts to solve the following problems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cleaning a dirty display&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keeping the device switched on without having to log out and log back in again&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keeping you in flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a fullscreen black screen app designed to show up dirt. Grab a screen wipe and wipe your laptop screen or your touch device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Touch support is patchy for now as the fullscreen API isn’t reliable on smaller displays. Rotating your iOS device will have the same effect for the meantime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turn into a bookmarklet rather than a bookmark&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Offer white alternative colour for stubborn stains&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2017 10:12:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://jordanm.co.uk/2017/08/20/released-wipe-screen.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jordanm.co.uk/2017/08/20/released-wipe-screen.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thoughts on human vs AI narration</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My Instapaper feed looks a lot like my Steam account. I have gathered many items with the good intention of making use of them on a rainy day, but they eventually gather dust on their virtual shelves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally I’ll try and blast through a set of articles that I considered at one point to have potential value to me. When I’m strapped for time I’ll try Instapaper’s “speak” feature, which is effectively a shortcut to iOS’ dictation feature. I usually end up cancelling the dictation after it reads a few paragraphs. Perhaps I forget how bad it is or maybe I’m expecting some advances in the technology since I last used it that make it sound more natural and human-like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With AI being applied to more and more tasks, fields and entire industries I notice how far it falls short of key human traits such as empathy and storytelling, and empathy within storytelling for that matter. We have thousands of years of experience on the robots when it comes to communicating oral wisdom from campfires and passing ideas down through generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI narration is improving, however, services like Narro offer bots with various dialects that have fairly accurate speech patterns and rhythm. But ultimately the narration ends up having a passive effect as AI hasn’t managed to emulate the human capability of captivating an audience to deliver a message. Robots rely on punctuation like a musical score to inform the pace at which they communicate text, though we lack punctuation for instinctive human storytelling tools like drama and the pause to allow certain ideas to simmer in the minds of the listener. This is why uninteresting speakers often fail to communicate their idea — the audience becomes disengaged from the message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a relevant note, another key human trait in storytelling is context. With a contextual understanding of the topic, humans know when to employ the storytelling tools mentioned previously. Consider this example from a recent opinion piece in the New York Times about the dangers of relying on Google rather than investing in deep understanding:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Google is good at finding information, but the brain beats it in two essential ways. Champions of Google underestimate how much the meaning of words and sentences changes with context. Consider vocabulary. Every teacher knows that a sixth grader, armed with a thesaurus, will often submit a paper studded with words used in not-quite-correct ways, like the student who looked up “meticulous,” saw it meant “very careful,” and wrote “I was meticulous when I fell off the cliff.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2017/05/19/opinion/sunday/you-still-need-your-brain.html&quot;&gt;From You Still Need Your Brain&lt;/a&gt; by Daniel T. Willingham&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A classic example of schoolchildren discovering a tool like a thesaurus and employing the technology incorrectly. With AI dictation we are cutting out the middleman leaving it open for potential missteps like this not necessarily with words, but the in the power of those words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S If you are looking for a startup idea, please feel free to design a subscription service with great human storytellers willing to read my Instapaper feed for me, thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2017 10:12:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://jordanm.co.uk/2017/06/04/thoughts-on-human-vs-ai-narration.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jordanm.co.uk/2017/06/04/thoughts-on-human-vs-ai-narration.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The power of awkward silence in user testing sessions</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Looking back over the vast majority of user testing sessions I have conducted, I noticed a pattern in where I felt I got the most value from each individual session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m talking about the moment where the room is silent and there’s that awkward pause where the user is struggling and everything in your being is telling you to help them. It’s the moment in the session when they’ve been struck by genuine confusion that causes a gap in the person articulating thoughts back to you as they move through the prototype. If you cave and give into your inherent human desire to help then you risk losing highly valuable insights. You’ll know that moment is happening because you’ll feel it in your gut. You’ll see the obvious on screen where the person sees something else. You’ll see it in their eyes and you’ll want to help by telling them the answer or even ask them something like “What did you expect to happen here?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exercise restraint and give that moment time to breathe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait for the silence to become uncomfortable and then keep waiting. If you speak first, you lose. Whatever they say first will be an insight. Even if it’s simply “I’m stuck…” or an “I don’t know what to do here…” that gives you a foundation upon which to build a line of questioning to dig deeper. Or they’ll tell you the answer and it will be gold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing that I’ve noticed is that after that moment in the session it’s generally the point at which the person loosens up a bit more and talks more candidly about their thought process and becomes more openly critical about your work. For me, this is what defines a useful user testing session versus a session resulting in a blank page with a lack of insights. Otherwise, we could end up going through the motions in a session where you both know the person isn’t being entirely honest because they don’t want to offend people and you end up receiving low-quality feedback, or some of the feedback simply isn’t communicated because that barrier hasn’t been removed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe it’s still important to lay the groundwork in making them feel at ease, like reassuring them that you didn’t design this thing and that it was the team back in the office (even though you totally designed it), and the fact that you’re helping us make this thing better (which is true) — it’s in that moment of awkwardness where they struggle and you exercise restraint — that’s where the real value lies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2017 10:12:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://jordanm.co.uk/2017/05/26/the-power-of-awkward-silence-during-user-testing-sessions.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jordanm.co.uk/2017/05/26/the-power-of-awkward-silence-during-user-testing-sessions.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Method UX</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Christian Bale famously lost 63lbs for the role of insomniac Trevor Reznik in Brad Anderson’s psychological thriller The Machinist. Bale’s disturbing body transformation happened over the course of 4 months during which he forced himself into a diet of a can of tuna and an apple per day, keeping himself isolated for prolonged periods of time and going without proper rest. His dedication to the role before filming even began is a common reference point for people describing method acting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Method acting is a technique derived from Constantin Stanislavski, a Russian actor and theatre director who between 1911 and 1916 used a methodology to train actors in the quest for theatrical truth. In essence the goals of Stanislavski’s System were to portray actors on stage as natural, believable characters. To achieve these goals actors would rely on recalling emotional memories and past experiences to bring those feelings to the role they had to portray. Actors would also use “If” (often refered to as the “Magic If”) to answer the question “What would I do if I was in this situation?” by envisioning themselves in the characters situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Christian Bale, many actors in the film industry such as Anne Hathaway, Robert De Niro and Joaquin Pheonix employ the modern day interpretation of Stanislavski’s System — method acting. The method starts before filming giving the actor time to plan and prepare for the role leaving them better equipped to deliver a stronger performance during filming with a relatable, believable character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t think that I’m suggesting that we as designers for the Web take on extreme diets or the kind of psychological experimentation that could be potentially damaging without professional advice. I can’t help but admire the lengths method actors go to for their art. Perhaps we can learn from the emotional investment they make to a role before production begins. Isn’t that the whole point of UX research? We throw the word “empathy” around boardrooms and company about pages to show that we care about the people we are making the product for. To me, empathy has become an empty promise - a buzzword to appease potential clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be truly empathetic I believe it involves going further than a few demographically informed personas that we assume are going to represent real people who use the things we make. Think about the project you’re working on now - how much of a difference would it make if you lived as the person you are making this for? How would they feel using the product? Where does it fit in their everyday lives? My hunch is that we would be able to make more well informed decisions that resonate with those people by diving right into the role, then we would have better tools to answer “What would I do if I was in this situation?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt that with this approach it can be emotionally taxing. There’s a balance and a scale in regards to how far you pursue it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After filming of The Machinist wrapped up Christian Bale’s next role was Bruce Wayne in Batman Begins. He gained 100lbs in six months and started rigourously learning martial arts for the many tightly choreographed fight sequences in the film.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2016 10:12:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://jordanm.co.uk/2016/07/13/method-ux.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jordanm.co.uk/2016/07/13/method-ux.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What I learned transitioning from agency to freelance</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Before I made the leap I read blog articles of other freelancers who did the same. People like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alwaystwisted.com/&quot;&gt;Stuart Robson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://cdja.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Chris Allwood&lt;/a&gt;, people who have made it work. I also called a &lt;strong&gt;lot&lt;/strong&gt; of people - &lt;a href=&quot;http://chris-armstrong.com/&quot;&gt;Chris Armstrong&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.christophermurphy.org/&quot;&gt;Chris Murphy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://theturf.io/&quot;&gt;Andrew Fulton&lt;/a&gt; - without their advice I probably would have talked myself out of it because before you actually do it your mind finds plenty of reasons not to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To cut to the chase: it’s working for me too, and I want to give that reassurance to people are considering making a similar move that it can work for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought I’d start by discussing a few of the worries I had after I handed in my notice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What if there isn’t enough work out there?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What about all that paperwork?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Running my own business sounds scary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly there is always work out there. This comes from a place of reassurance rather than any sort of attempt at bragging but my diary has been full since I began. I haven’t needed to advertise my services,apart from the initial announcement in March that I was going freelance. Since then I’ve found traditional word of mouth is still the most effective form of advertising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to let word of mouth do the work for you is to turn up every day and do the best job you can do. One of the biggest differences between agency and freelance work is that in an agency environment I would plan out how the next day or in some cases how the next week would look. Now that I work for myself I need to know what the next 3 months look like to ensure the pipeline is healthy and that I can continue to work for a variety of different people on different design problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paperwork was strangely my biggest worry. I’ve never owned a business, I’ve produced invoices and estimates before in both of my previous agencies, but not for my own business. I worried that there might have been other paperwork that I hadn’t been exposed to before and that perhaps the amount of paperwork would have been overwhelming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily clever companies have been solving this problem. I bought a subscription to &lt;a href=&quot;http://fre.ag/44l7su5c&quot;&gt;FreeAgent&lt;/a&gt; which handles my accounts including estimates, changing estimates into invoices, sending out invoice reminders, it keeps everything in check for things like tax returns and expenses. Without it, I’d be putting so much more time into this side of the business rather than concentrating on the fun, rewarding stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most exciting aspects of working for myself has been applying the knowledge I’ve gained after over 7 years of industry experience. I’ve learned from some great people like Paul May how could apply analytical thinking to design problems and could lead effective workshops with stakeholders and get the most out of people’s time. I’ve learned from Paul McKeever’s ability to find, create and deliver value for users and clients alike, and I’ve also borrowed heavily from Jamie Neely’s design theory and reasoning to ensure everything I make serves a purpose and fulfills a need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By observing and working with great people, it’s easier to deliver great work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same is true today, if I take on a project where I know someone can specialise on a particular component, I have the flexibility to hire people in and apply their skills. Working with be best helps you keep performing to your best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the work itself I have adapted to the freelance lifestyle pretty quickly. I have taken the time to study when I’m most productive and shape my working day around those hours. This means I know when I can do my best work rather than working within a set period of hours that the rest of a team works within.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That flexibility extends to the working environment. If I’m bored of working at my desk I can take my office with me to somewhere else like a coffee shop, or another studio, the library - wherever I want to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve even worked a few evenings during my summer holidays - I wouldn’t recommend it for most people if you want to unwind, but I rather enjoy the novelty of working in a different country on the same projects I’ve been working on from home. It means the holidays themselves can be more flexible too - next year I’m considering working from the US for a couple of months and making the most of the school holidays with my family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last point I want to make is the most important factor in my decision to go freelance. I went from seeing my kids for 1-2 hours a day to being able to drop them to school, pick them up from school, attend sports days, I’ve been able to &lt;strong&gt;be there&lt;/strong&gt;. That’s the kind of freedom that I enjoy most aside from all the other benefits. I can watch my young family grow up much more closely than I have before, and the best part is they don’t grow up so fast anymore because I’m there to see so more of it and spend time with them. It’s our most precious commodity and now I can shape my time to fit however I want rather than being told how to spend it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2015 10:12:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://jordanm.co.uk/2015/10/18/freelance-vs-agency.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jordanm.co.uk/2015/10/18/freelance-vs-agency.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Going Freelance</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I am delighted to announce that after 7 years working in web agencies I have decided to leave and start a new adventure as a freelance web designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I joined Front in 2008 midway through my final year of university, I have spent the last 7 years honing my craft specialising in &lt;strong&gt;responsive web design&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;user experience&lt;/strong&gt; as well as &lt;strong&gt;front end&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Expression Engine development&lt;/strong&gt;. I believe that being part of the team with Front (now known as Typecast) and Eyekiller has equipped me with the skills required to manage my own destiny and seek new and exciting projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working and collaborating closely with clients of all different shapes and sizes from various sectors including the BBC, Firefly and TextHelp and has been a truly invaluable experience. I’ll miss working with my fantastic clients - it has been a priviledge working together with &lt;strong&gt;each and every one of you&lt;/strong&gt; to make useful, meaningful things for the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course I will miss working alongside the wonderful team at Eyekiller. I have made many friends since I joined in 2012. My last day is just under a month away on April 1st 2015. If you have any projects you would like to discuss with me, please feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#098;&amp;#121;&amp;#106;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#100;&amp;#097;&amp;#110;&amp;#064;&amp;#103;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#046;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&quot;&gt;get in touch&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2015 09:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://jordanm.co.uk/2015/03/03/going-freelance.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jordanm.co.uk/2015/03/03/going-freelance.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
